<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Conj | An Architect's View]]></title>
  <link href="http://corfield.org/blog/categories/conj/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://corfield.org/"/>
  <updated>2019-12-31T21:44:50-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://corfield.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Sean Corfield]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Excited About Clojure/conj]]></title>
    <link href="http://corfield.org/blog/2018/10/25/clojure-conj/"/>
    <updated>2018-10-25T03:40:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://corfield.org/blog/2018/10/25/clojure-conj</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It has been a crazy busy year, both at work and personally, and it&rsquo;s hard for me to believe my last blog post was in April!</p>

<p><a href="https://2018.clojure-conj.org/">Clojure/conj</a> is coming up fast and the schedule was posted today, which has made me even more excited about it. Here&rsquo;s a run down of the sessions I plan to attend &ndash; I&rsquo;ll write up my thoughts on everything shortly after the conference.</p>

<ul>
<li>Welcome Event &ndash; I&rsquo;m hoping my flight is on time and Lyft can get me there in time to chill and network with all the interesting Clojurians!</li>
<li>Stuart Halloway &ndash; In his recent <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6ftW8UwwP_4">Apropos podcast</a>, he hinted that this talk would be about new tooling he has been using. Maybe prepl-related?</li>
<li>Christopher Small &ndash; Clojure on the cyberpunk frontier of democracy &ndash; This sounds fascinating.</li>
<li>Chris Johnson Bidler &ndash; Serverless-ish: Zero to App with Datomic Cloud and GraphQL.</li>
<li>Ghadi Shayban &ndash; Java Made (Somewhat) Simple &ndash; Although Ghadi told me this might be a beginner/intermediate-level talk, he&rsquo;s a great speaker and I look forward to hearing his insights about the platform.</li>
<li>Boris Kourtoukov &ndash; Machines that Judge Us.</li>
<li>Tiago Luchini &ndash; Declarative Domain Modeling for Datomic Ion/Cloud.</li>
<li>Lily Goh + Dom Kiva-Meyer &ndash; Robust APIs with clojure.spec &amp; GraphQL &ndash; I&rsquo;m a huge advocate of spec and we&rsquo;re also using GraphQL at work so this should be very applicable.</li>
<li>Rich Hickey &ndash; Maybe Not &ndash; Rich is always worth the price of entry!</li>
<li>Unsessions &ndash; Looking forward to seeing the schedule for these. Past years' unsessions have included some real diamonds!</li>
<li>David Chelimsky &ndash; AWS, meet Clojure.</li>
<li>Ben Kamphaus &ndash; AI Systems: Foundations for Artificial Minds or Aaron Cummings &ndash; Making Memories: Clojure For Hardware Engineers (And Others). I&rsquo;m undecided but leaning toward the AI talk.</li>
<li>Elena Machkasova &ndash; Babel: middleware for beginner-friendly error messages &ndash; Anything that helps with Clojure&rsquo;s error messages (much improved in Clojure 1.10!) is always worth learning about!</li>
<li>Wilker Lucio da Silva &ndash; Scaling Full-Stack Applications Over Hundreds of Microservices or Daniel Gregoire &ndash; Tables Considered Helpful. Undecided again but leaning toward the table talk.</li>
<li>Nikolas Göbel &ndash; Reactive Datalog for Datomic or Tyler Hobbs &ndash; Code goes in, Art comes out. Undecided but leaning toward the Datalog talk (because I&rsquo;m not hugely interested in art/computing).</li>
<li>Gary Fredericks &ndash; What Are All These Class Files Even About? And Other Stories &ndash; Having been repeatedly bitten by AOT, I&rsquo;m looking forward to this!</li>
<li>Tomomi Livingstone + Hans Livingstone &ndash; Party REPL — A multi-player REPL built for pair-programming &ndash; This looks very, very interesting!</li>
<li>Rebecca Parsons &ndash; Closing day two keynote.</li>
<li>(Party!)</li>
<li>Carin Meier &ndash; Can you GAN? &ndash; No idea about the topic but Carin is always an engaging speaker.</li>
<li>Dave Fetterman &ndash; Learning and Teaching Clojure on the job at Amperity &ndash; Because coming up to speed (and bringing others up to speed) is important.</li>
<li>Vikash Mansinghka &ndash; Probabilistic programming and meta-programming in Clojure &ndash; WAT?</li>
<li>Alex Engelberg and Derek Slager &ndash; Every Clojure Talk Ever &ndash; Cryptically enticing&hellip;</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
