<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Jdbc | An Architect's View]]></title>
  <link href="http://corfield.org/blog/categories/jdbc/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://corfield.org/"/>
  <updated>2019-06-04T18:29:06-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://corfield.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Sean Corfield]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Next.JDBC Beta 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://corfield.org/blog/2019/06/04/next-jdbc/"/>
    <updated>2019-06-04T11:30:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://corfield.org/blog/2019/06/04/next-jdbc</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1>seancorfield/next.jdbc 1.0.0-rc1</h1>

<p><code>next.jdbc</code> &ndash; the &ldquo;next generation&rdquo; of <code>clojure.java.jdbc</code> &ndash; is a modern Clojure wrapper for JDBC. The first Release Candidate is now available to test &ndash; containing only accretive and fixative changes from Beta 1. The API should be considered stable enough for production usage.</p>

<p><a href="https://cljdoc.org/d/seancorfield/next.jdbc/1.0.0-rc1/doc/readme">https://cljdoc.org/d/seancorfield/next.jdbc/1.0.0-rc1/doc/readme</a></p>

<p>The focus of this release is providing more flexibility in result set builders, so that it is easier to implement your own naming strategies, via new builders that accept <code>:label-fn</code> and <code>:qualifier-fn</code> options. These mirror the <code>:column-fn</code> and <code>:table-fn</code> options used in <code>next.jdbc.sql</code> &ndash; which are updated versions of <code>clojure.java.jdbc</code>&rsquo;s <code>:entities</code> option. These new builder options are updated versions of <code>clojure.java.jdbc</code>&rsquo;s <code>:identifiers</code> option.</p>

<h2>Changes since Beta 1</h2>

<ul>
<li>Fix #24 by adding return type hints to <code>next.jdbc</code> functions.</li>
<li>Fix #22 by adding <code>next.jdbc.optional</code> with six map builders that omit <code>NULL</code> columns from the row hash maps.</li>
<li>Documentation improvements (#27, #28, and #29), including changing &ldquo;connectable&rdquo; to &ldquo;transactable&rdquo; for the <code>transact</code> function and the <code>with-transaction</code> macro (for consistency with the name of the underlying protocol).</li>
<li>Fix #30 by adding <code>modified</code> variants of column name functions and builders. The <code>lower</code> variants have been rewritten in terms of these new <code>modified</code> variants. This adds <code>:label-fn</code> and <code>:qualifier-fn</code> options that mirror <code>:column-fn</code> and <code>:table-fn</code> for row builders.</li>
</ul>


<p>Please take it for a test drive and let me know if you run into any problems via <a href="https://github.com/seancorfield/next-jdbc/issues">GitHub issues</a> or in the <a href="https://clojurians.slack.com/messages/C1Q164V29/details/"><code>#sql</code> channel on the Clojurians Slack</a> or the <a href="https://clojurians.zulipchat.com/#narrow/stream/152063-sql"><code>#sql</code> stream on the Clojurians Zulip</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Next.JDBC Beta 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://corfield.org/blog/2019/05/25/next-jdbc/"/>
    <updated>2019-05-25T08:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://corfield.org/blog/2019/05/25/next-jdbc</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1>seancorfield/next.jdbc 1.0.0-beta1</h1>

<p><code>next.jdbc</code> &ndash; the &ldquo;next generation&rdquo; of <code>clojure.java.jdbc</code> &ndash; is a modern Clojure wrapper for JDBC. Beta 1 is now available to test &ndash; only accretive and fixative changes will be made from this point on, so the API should be considered stable enough for production usage.</p>

<p><a href="https://cljdoc.org/d/seancorfield/next.jdbc/1.0.0-beta1/doc/readme">https://cljdoc.org/d/seancorfield/next.jdbc/1.0.0-beta1/doc/readme</a></p>

<p>The group and artifact ID will remain <code>seancorfield/next.jdbc</code>, the namespace structure will remain <code>next.jdbc.*</code>. With auto-generated documentation hosted on cljdoc.org and Continuous Integration testing hosted on circleci.com, I have decided to continue work on <code>next.jdbc</code> outside Clojure Contrib, rather than merge it into <code>clojure.java.jdbc</code> as new namespaces there. I have updated the <a href="https://github.com/seancorfield/next-jdbc/blob/master/CONTRIBUTING.md">Contributing page on GitHub</a> to reflect that Pull Requests can now be submitted.</p>

<h2>Changes since Alpha 13</h2>

<ul>
<li>Set up CircleCI testing (just local DBs for now).</li>
<li>Address <a href="https://github.com/seancorfield/next-jdbc/issues/21">#21</a> by adding <code>next.jdbc.specs</code> and documenting basic usage.</li>
<li>Fix <a href="https://github.com/seancorfield/next-jdbc/issues/19">#19</a> by caching loaded database driver classes.</li>
<li>Address <a href="https://github.com/seancorfield/next-jdbc/issues/16">#16</a> by renaming <code>reducible!</code> to <code>plan</code> (this is a <strong>BREAKING CHANGE!</strong> from Alpha 13 &ndash; the naming of this function was the blocker for moving from Alpha to Beta).</li>
<li>Address <a href="https://github.com/seancorfield/next-jdbc/issues/3">#3</a> by deciding to maintain this library outside Clojure Contrib.</li>
</ul>


<p>Please take it for a test drive and let me know if you run into any problems via <a href="https://github.com/seancorfield/next-jdbc/issues">GitHub issues</a> or in the <a href="https://clojurians.slack.com/messages/C1Q164V29/details/"><code>#sql</code> channel on the Clojurians Slack</a> or the <a href="https://clojurians.zulipchat.com/#narrow/stream/152063-sql"><code>#sql</code> stream on the Clojurians Zulip</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Next.JDBC]]></title>
    <link href="http://corfield.org/blog/2019/04/21/next-jdbc/"/>
    <updated>2019-04-21T16:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://corfield.org/blog/2019/04/21/next-jdbc</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1>seancorfield/next.jdbc 1.0.0-alpha8</h1>

<p>I&rsquo;ve talked about this in a few groups &ndash; it&rsquo;s been a long time coming. This is the &ldquo;next generation&rdquo; of <code>clojure.java.jdbc</code> &ndash; a modern wrapper for JDBC, that focuses on <code>reduce</code>/transducers, qualified-keywords, and <code>datafy</code>/<code>nav</code> support (so, yes, it requires Clojure 1.10).</p>

<p><a href="https://cljdoc.org/d/seancorfield/next.jdbc/1.0.0-alpha8/doc/readme">https://cljdoc.org/d/seancorfield/next.jdbc/1.0.0-alpha8/doc/readme</a></p>

<p><em>The next generation of <code>clojure.java.jdbc</code>: a new low-level Clojure wrapper for JDBC-based access to databases.</em>  It&rsquo;s intended to be both faster and simpler than <code>clojure.java.jdbc</code> and it&rsquo;s where I intend to focus my future energy, although I have not yet decided whether it will ultimately be a new set of namespaces in the Contrib lib or a separate, standalone OSS library!</p>

<p>At this point, I&rsquo;m looking for feedback on the API and the approach (as well as bugs, performance issues, etc). Please take it for a spin and let me know what you think via <a href="https://github.com/seancorfield/next-jdbc/issues">GitHub issues</a> or in the <a href="https://clojurians.slack.com/messages/C1Q164V29/details/"><code>#sql</code> channel on the Clojurians Slack</a> or the <a href="https://clojurians.zulipchat.com/#narrow/stream/152063-sql"><code>#sql</code> stream on the Clojurians Zulip</a>.</p>

<p><em>The group/artifact ID will change at some point:</em> and the actual namespaces will too, but I will try to make that as painless as possible when I take this out of the alpha phase.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SQL NULL, S/nilable, and Optionality]]></title>
    <link href="http://corfield.org/blog/2018/12/06/null-nilable-optionality/"/>
    <updated>2018-12-06T03:30:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://corfield.org/blog/2018/12/06/null-nilable-optionality</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Rich Hickey gave a very thought-provoking talk at Clojure/conj 2018
called <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YR5WdGrpoug&amp;list=PLZdCLR02grLpMkEBXT22FTaJYxB92i3V3&amp;index=2">Maybe Not</a>, where he mused
on optionality and how we represent the absence of a value.<!-- more --></p>

<p>His talk covered many things, including how <code>clojure.spec/keys</code> currently
complects both structure and optionality (and his thoughts on fixing that
in a future version of <code>clojure.spec</code>), but his mention of <code>s/nilable</code> was what
triggered an &ldquo;ah-ha!&rdquo; moment for me.</p>

<p>At <a href="https://worldsinglesnetworks.com">World Singles Networks</a>, we deal with a lot
of data in SQL (specifically in Percona&rsquo;s fork of MySQL) and, in SQL, you represent
the absence of a value with <code>NULL</code> in a column. Columns that represent optional
data must be declared as nullable and when you read data from them with
<a href="https://github.com/clojure/java.jdbc">clojure.java.jdbc</a> you get hash map
entries in the rows that have <code>nil</code> values. If you&rsquo;re using <code>clojure.spec</code> to
describe your tables, rows, and columns, then you are going to have lots of
<code>s/nilable</code> specs &ndash; and now your &ldquo;optionality&rdquo; has been reified into <code>nil</code>
values, cast in the stone of your specs&hellip; which is clearly not an ideal situation!</p>

<p>This made me realize that <code>java.jdbc</code> probably should just omit keys whose
values represent SQL <code>NULL</code>. They are, after all, <em>optional</em> values rather than
truly <em>nilable</em> values.</p>

<p>That would be a potentially breaking change in behavior for <code>java.jdbc</code> users.
Sure, in most cases, if you have a hash map representing a row in a database
table, you&rsquo;re not really going to care whether <code>(:col row)</code> gives you <code>nil</code>
because <code>:col</code> maps to <code>nil</code> or because <code>row</code> doesn&rsquo;t contain <code>:col</code>. There are
use cases where it matters: <code>contains?</code>, row/column specs, tabular printing.</p>

<p>Along with changing the behavior of <code>NULL</code> columns and
<a href="http://corfield.org/blog/2018/12/03/datafy-nav/">supporting <code>datafy</code> and <code>nav</code></a>,
I have a lot of other changes that I&rsquo;d like to apply to <code>java.jdbc</code>, such as
automatically qualifying column keys with the table from which they came,
improving overall performance (by no longer converting <code>ResultSet</code> objects to
sequences of hash maps), dramatically simplifying and streamlining the options
that are available (since many of them are very rarely used), and focusing on a
reducible-first API. All of which would be breaking changes.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve learned a lot &ndash; about Clojure, idioms, and databases &ndash; over the seven
years that I&rsquo;ve been maintaining <code>org.clojure/java.jdbc</code>, and it is time for a
new namespace or perhaps even a completely new project, that offers a better
way to deal with SQL databases from Clojure! I&rsquo;ll be writing a series of blog
posts about the differences I envisage between the current de facto standard
JDBC wrapper and where I&rsquo;d like to go with this, so that I can get community
feedback on what should stay, what should change, and what should go. Stay tuned!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Clojure 1.10's Datafy and Nav]]></title>
    <link href="http://corfield.org/blog/2018/12/03/datafy-nav/"/>
    <updated>2018-12-03T09:20:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://corfield.org/blog/2018/12/03/datafy-nav</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the more mysterious new features in Clojure 1.10 seems to be the pairing of <a href="https://github.com/clojure/clojure/blob/master/changes.md#26-datafy-and-nav"><code>datafy</code> and <code>nav</code></a> (and their underlying protocols, <code>Datafiable</code> and <code>Navigable</code>). Interest in these new functions has been piqued after Stuart Halloway showed off <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=c52QhiXsmyI&amp;list=PLZdCLR02grLpMkEBXT22FTaJYxB92i3V3&amp;index=3">REBL at Clojure/conj</a> (video). Stu presented this functionality as &ldquo;generalized laziness&rdquo;: <code>datafy</code> produces a &ldquo;data representation&rdquo; of things and <code>nav</code> lets you (lazily) navigate around that data.<!-- more --></p>

<p>The <a href="http://rebl.cognitect.com/">REBL</a> &ldquo;is a graphical, interactive tool for browsing Clojure data&rdquo;. And in Clojure we&rsquo;re used to the concept of &ldquo;it&rsquo;s just data&rdquo; so a graphical browser might sound useful but not exactly earthshaking. But REBL is just an example of what can be built with the new functionality in 1.10 and, indeed, Stu&rsquo;s claim of &ldquo;generalized laziness&rdquo; is well made but a little hard to grok until you actually build something with the new protocols and functions.</p>

<p>Since I&rsquo;ve done exactly that &ndash; with experimental support for <a href="https://github.com/clojure/java.jdbc/blob/master/src/main/clojure/clojure/java/jdbc/datafy.clj">lazy navigation of related records in <code>java.jdbc</code></a> &ndash; and spent some time on Slack today explaining how it all works, I figured it would be worth writing down in a more permanent place, as a blog post.</p>

<p>The <code>Datafiable</code> protocol (new in <code>clojure.core.protocols</code>) is defined for <code>nil</code> and <code>Object</code> to just return those values as-is, and then extended in <code>clojure.datafy</code> to cover:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>Throwable</code> &ndash; producing a simple hash map by calling <code>Throwable-&gt;map</code></li>
<li><code>clojure.lang.IRef</code> &ndash; producing a vector containing the dereferenced value, with the original metadata from the reference attached to that vector</li>
<li><code>clojure.lang.Namespace</code> &ndash; producing a hash map that is the data representation of the namespace (<code>:name</code>, <code>:publics</code>, <code>:imports</code>, and <code>:interns</code>) with the metadata of the namespace attached</li>
<li><code>java.lang.Class</code> &ndash; producing the <code>clojure.reflect/reflect</code> representation of the class, with an additional member <code>:name</code>, and the <code>:members</code> of the class grouped by name and sorted</li>
</ul>


<p>The <code>Navigable</code> protocol (new in <code>clojure.core.protocols</code>) is defined just for <code>Object</code> and, given some sort of object or collection, some sort of &ldquo;key&rdquo;, and a value, it will just return the value itself.</p>

<p>Based on that, it may not be clear how to implement the protocols or use the functions. The key thing that may not be obvious here is that <code>datafy</code> is intended to convert an arbitrary &ldquo;thing&rdquo; of any type into a pure Clojure data representation and, from that starting point, you can then use <code>nav</code> to &ldquo;navigate&rdquo; to a value derived from the original &ldquo;thing&rdquo;, which you would then process with <code>datafy</code> to get a pure Clojure data representation again. Those data representations may contain pieces that satisfy the <code>Navigable</code> protocol so that navigation (via <code>nav</code>) provides more than just a simple data-level lookup.</p>

<p>Using the <code>clojure.java.jdbc.datafy</code> code as an example, you would call <code>query</code> (from that new namespace) and get back a result set. That looks like a sequence of hash maps (rows) but adds metadata to the rows that provides an implementation of <code>Datafiable</code> (<a href="https://github.com/clojure/clojure/blob/master/changes.md#22-protocol-extension-by-metadata">protocol extension via metadata</a> is also new in Clojure 1.10). The row is the &ldquo;arbitrary thing&rdquo; that we are starting with. One or more of the columns in that row may be a foreign key into another table. When you turn the row into a pure Clojure data representation &ndash; by calling <code>datafy</code> on it &ndash; it still looks like a hash map but now it has metadata that provides an implementation of <code>Navigable</code>. That supports calling <code>(nav row column value)</code> and, if the column is considered to be a foreign key to another table, it will fetch the relevant row(s) from that table and return that as the next &ldquo;arbitrary thing&rdquo;, otherwise it will just return the column&rsquo;s value as passed in. The cycle of converting that to data (via <code>datafy</code>) and navigating through it (by navigating the Clojure data and then calling <code>nav</code> on that) can be continued indefinitely, until you bottom out to simple values.</p>

<p>You can sum this up as:</p>

<ul>
<li>Starting with a &ldquo;thing&rdquo;&hellip;</li>
<li>&hellip;you convert it to data (with <code>datafy</code>)&hellip;</li>
<li>&hellip;and walk it with simple Clojure data access&hellip;</li>
<li>&hellip;and, at each stage, you can navigate to the corresponding &ldquo;new thing&rdquo; by calling <code>nav</code>&hellip;</li>
<li>&hellip;which may return just that value or may do something more complex&hellip;</li>
<li>&hellip;and from that &ldquo;new thing&rdquo; you convert it to data (with <code>datafy</code>) and continue the process.</li>
</ul>


<p>Relating this back to REBL, it works by taking some arbitrary value produced in the REPL and converting it to data (via <code>datafy</code>) so that it can be displayed in the UI. With any part of that data highlighted you can &ldquo;drill down&rdquo;, at which point REBL calls <code>nav</code> to perform the (potentially lazy, complex) navigation and then converts that to data (via <code>datafy</code>) and displays that as the next &ldquo;level&rdquo; of data. Given an associative data representation, it does <code>(get coll k)</code> first to get <code>v</code>, and then it calls <code>(nav coll k v)</code> to allow the underlying navigation to return an updated value.</p>

<p>You go from &ldquo;thing&rdquo; to &ldquo;data representation&rdquo; of &ldquo;thing&rdquo; (via <code>datafy</code>), and then you can do the simple associative lookup <em>in the data representation, not the original thing</em>, and then you use <code>nav</code> to get back to the relevant equivalent part of the &ldquo;thing&rdquo;, and then you <code>datafy</code> that again to get pure data. For built-in Clojure data types that are already pure data, <code>datafy</code> does nothing and <code>nav</code> just returns the selected value. For hash maps, navigation is just simple key lookup. For vectors, navigation is also simple key (index) lookup. This new machinery only starts to shine in more complex situations.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
